<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon preached before the Queen at White-Hall, August 21, 1692 by Nathanael Resbury ...</title>
            <author>Resbury, Nathanael, 1643-1711.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1692</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 33 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 17 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A57063</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing R1133</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R35361</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">15264730</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 15264730</idno>
            <idno type="VID">103312</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A57063)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 103312)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1192:19)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon preached before the Queen at White-Hall, August 21, 1692 by Nathanael Resbury ...</title>
                  <author>Resbury, Nathanael, 1643-1711.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>32 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Tho. Bennet ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1692.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Half-title page reads: Dr. Resbury's sermon preached before the Queen at White-Hall, August 21, 1692.</note>
                  <note>"Published by Her Majesty's special command."</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  O.T. --  Job XXXIII, 22-24 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="half_title">
            <pb facs="tcp:103312:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Dr. <hi>RESBURY</hi>'s SERMON Preached before the QUEEN AT WHITE-HALL, <hi>Auguſt</hi> 21. 1692.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:103312:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:103312:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A SERMON Preached before the QUEEN AT WHITE-HALL, Auguſt 21. 1692.</p>
            <p>By <hi>NATHANAEL RESBURY,</hi> D. D. Rector of S. <hi>Paul Shadwell,</hi> and Chaplain in Ordinary to Their Majeſties.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Publiſhed by Her Majeſty's Special Command.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Tho. Bennet</hi> at the <hi>Half-Moon</hi> in St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Church-yard, 1692.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:103312:3"/>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:103312:3"/>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Job xxxiij. 22, 23, 24.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <q>His ſoul draweth near unto the grave, and his life to the deſtroyers. If there be a meſſenger with him, an interpreter, one among a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand, to ſhew unto Man his uprightneſs: Then is he gracious unto him, and ſaith, Deliver him from going down unto the pit; I have found a ranſom.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>THeſe words have ſomething in them, that ſeems dark and myſterious, as a great many paſſages, in this Book of <hi>Job</hi> particularly, have. It is one entire and lofty Poem, and not onely ſo, but one of the ancienteſt pieces of Writing that was ever deliver'd to the World; and ſo, muſt needs have things in it very difficult; being either Proverbial expreſſions, peculiar to the Age or Countries amongſt whom they were then in uſe, or elſe References to the Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtories of thoſe Times; which being now wholly out of reach, render the paſſages that concern them, ſo much the more ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruſe and unintelligible. However, if we conſider the drift of this <hi>Chapter,</hi> where my
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:103312:4"/>Text is, it may make for clearing up theſe words, and the deſign of that Subject of diſcourſe I intend from them.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Elihu,</hi> one of <hi>Job</hi>'s Viſitants, is remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bring him of the various methods God is pleas'd to take, in teaching and diſcipli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning Mankind; with all his gracious Ends and Deſigns in theſe ways of inſtruction, <hi>viz.</hi> to bring Men to the knowledge both of God himſelf, and of their own ſtate. He ſhows further, all thoſe mixtures of goodneſs, the ſoftnings and mitigations, the allays or refreſhments, that God is pleas'd to miniſter, even under the ſharpeſt afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, which he thinks fit ſometimes to bring upon Men.</p>
            <p>The ways of inſtruction repreſented in this <hi>Chapter,</hi> are,</p>
            <p n="1">1. By <hi>Viſions</hi> or <hi>Night-dreams.</hi> When the Mind was retir'd from the buſineſs and noiſe of the day, and was more receptive of di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine impreſſions. A way, which it pleas'd God to take ſomething more frequently, as a Miniſtry of knowledge, when Men had no other ſupply of Revelation; no written Oracles of God for a rule and ſtandard of their belief and actions. <hi>Ver.</hi> 14, 15, 16. <hi>God
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:103312:4"/>ſpeaketh once, yea twice, yet man perceiveth it not. In a Dream, in a Viſion of the night—then he openeth the Ears of men and ſealeth their inſtruction.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But then, as God was wont to inſtruct Mankind, by <hi>Viſions</hi> or <hi>Dreams,</hi> ſo he had another way, and that more uſual, that which (as it might be circumſtanc'd) might prove much more inſtructive, more effectual for his correction and amendment every way.</p>
            <p>And this was, by afflictions and calamities of life: Eſpecially <hi>Diſeaſes</hi> and <hi>Sickneſſes,</hi> which were not intended meerly to afflict Mankind, or make their lives uneaſie or un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comfortable; but to give them a ſight of themſelves, to remember them of their guilt to teach them their duty, how they may learn to carry themſelves before God, with all ſubmiſſion to his Will, dependance upon his Providence, and repentance for the irre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gularities of Life, by which they have pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vok'd God. <hi>Ver.</hi> 19. and ſo on. <hi>He is cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſten'd alſo with pains upon his bed, and the multitude of his bones with ſtrong pain, ſo that his life abhorreth bread, and his ſoul dainty meat.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:103312:5"/>
—<hi>His ſoul draweth near unto the grave, and his life to the deſtroyers.</hi>—And this way of inſtruction, as <hi>Job</hi> himſelf was at preſent under; ſo <hi>Elihu,</hi> in deſcribing it, ſeems to accommodate his Expreſſions to the cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances of <hi>Job</hi>'s Sickneſs; to the allays and mitigations he might obſerve in them, and to the hopes he might have of a good iſſue and deliverance out of them. The circumſtances of his diſeaſe, he deſcribes by the pains in his bones, the weakneſs of his ſtomach, the conſumption of his fleſh, and that degree of waſting, that he ſeems (as we expreſs it) as if he were juſt drawing on. <hi>His ſoul draweth near unto the grave.</hi> The allays and mitigations he might obſerve were theſe; That he had thoſe about him, that might inſtruct him in the Will of God; that might bring him to a ſenſe of himſelf; that might interpoſe with God in his behalf, and prevail for the removal of this preſent affliction. <hi>If there be a meſſenger with him, an interpreter, one among a thouſand, to ſhow unto man his uprightneſs: Then he is gracious unto him, and ſaith, Deliver him from going down unto the pit; I have found a ranſom.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:103312:5"/>
Laſtly, The encouraging hopes he might have of a reſcue from death (tho' his diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſe look't very dangerouſly) <hi>ver.</hi> 25, 26. <hi>His fleſh ſhall be freſher than a Child's, he ſhall return to the days of his youth, he ſhall pray unto God, and he will be favourable unto him, and he ſhall ſee his face with joy.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the words thus explain'd, by what went before, and what follow after, there may ariſe theſe three Things obſervable.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The great incidency of humane Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture to ſickneſs and bodily diſeaſes; <hi>His ſoul draweth near to the grave,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p n="2">2. That ſickneſs and bodily diſeaſes, to which humane Nature is ſo incident, have a great deal of inſtruction in them; and it pleaſeth God frequently to inflict them for this very end; that Men might be taught the knowledge of themſelves, and their duty toward Him. This I gather from the ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dency of the Argument that <hi>Elihu</hi> is upon; <hi>viz.</hi> ſhowing the various methods by which it pleaſeth God to teach Men the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of his Will; ſometimes by <hi>Viſions</hi> and <hi>Dreams in the night;</hi> at other times, by <hi>ſick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs</hi> and other <hi>calamities.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:103312:6"/>
3. Laſtly, It is further obſervable how great a bleſſing of Providence it is, and what an allay to the affliction, to enjoy one of the <hi>Meſſengers</hi> of God about a Sick-bed. Some excellent Perſon that may read Lec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures upon Divine Providence, that may govern us in our behaviour toward God when under his correction and chaſtiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and that may pray in our behalves for the removal of that Calamity, in his own good time. <hi>If there be a meſſenger with him, an interpreter, one among a thouſand, to ſhew unto man his uprightneſs,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Of theſe in their Order.</p>
            <p n="1">I. I obſerve to you the great incidency of humane Nature to ſickneſs and bodily diſeaſes. The beſt of Men are not exempt from them. We have two great inſtances in <hi>Job</hi> and <hi>David;</hi> who both fell not onely under the power of common diſtempers, and weakneſſes of body, but diſeaſes, as ſoul and noiſom, as ſore and painfull, as ſtrange and exemplary, as have ever yet befallen the worſt of Men. And as the beſt of Men are not exempt, ſo neither are the youngeſt, nor thoſe of the ſtrongeſt conſtitution. We
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:103312:6"/>may be gay and flouriſhing in all the Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gours of youth and health to day, and to morrow groaning under the pains and lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhings of a ſick-bed; not able to move an arme, or wink into a moment's reſt; not able to bear the leaſt food or ſupport of Nature, much leſs to exerciſe the nobler faculties of Mind in any juſt thought or act of good reaſoning.</p>
            <p>This incidency to ſickneſs and bodily diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſes is founded, partly in the frame of our Natures, partly the common Accidents of Life, but eſpecially (and without which, that Divine Hand that made us, would have ſecur'd us againſt all the Accidents of our nice and tender Compoſure) the great in-let to all Calamity, Sin, and our fatal A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtaſie from God.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The very frame of our Natures. We are ſo fine a piece of Workmanſhip, wrought off with ſuch Applications of Wiſdom as well as Power, and made up of ſuch num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berleſs dependencies, all ſo tender, and ſo eaſily interrupted; that, were we to conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the ſtructure of our bodies, the ſmall fibers, the neceſſary communication of parts, the ſtrange ways of conveyance for
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:103312:7"/>the nouriſhment of the whole, it might rather be a wonder every moment that we feel our ſelves in health and order, than any ſurprize to labour under an indiſpos'd Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, which may be ſo eaſily over turn'd by any peccant humour, by the leaſt ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction in any of its parts, by the redun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dancy, as well as defect, or decay of what, in a juſt and equal temperament, might be our ſupport and defence. However, ſuch is indeed our Contexture and Frame, that the very neceſſary uſe and exerciſe of the ſeveral parts for the maintenance of the whole, and of one another, do's wear and decay them, takes off their natural ſervice, brings in a gradual death upon ſome of our parts, which becomes paſt all poſſibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity of repair or revival, and (as the Learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Lord <hi>Verulam</hi> ſomewhere obſerves) <q>puts us, in old Age, under the torments of <hi>Mezentius,</hi> that is, tyes the living to the dead; parts that are decay'd, and have ceas'd their Functions, to thoſe that are alive and animated, and ſtill at work, for the meer continuance of life and action.</q> So that Old Age is one natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral and unavoidable diſeaſe, which the
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:103312:7"/>ſtrongeſt, the beſt compos'd, the beſt us'd Conſtitution cannot but fall under. And thus the <hi>Wiſe man</hi> deſcribes all the parts and organs of the Body, as having by degrees ſpent themſelves off, into a perfect unſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viceableneſs in Old age, till the whole ſtructure it ſelf comes to fall and be demo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh'd, <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 12.2, 3, 6. When <hi>the Sun, or the Light, or the Moon, or the Stars begin to be darken'd.</hi> When <hi>the keepers of the houſe tremble, the ſtrong men bowe themſelves, and the grinders ceaſe, and they that look out of the windows be darken'd</hi>—When <hi>the ſilver cord is loos'd, and the golden bowl is broken, or the pitcher broken at the fountain, or the wheel bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken at the ciſtern,</hi> &amp;c. <q>That is, when all the faculties and powers of the Soul, the leading and the rational, the lower and the ſenſitive, ſhall begin to be obſtructed in their ſeveral operations; and when the members of the Body ſhall betray their ſenſible decays: the nerves looſe and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feebl'd, the ſpirits low and unactive, the leggs and hands trembling, the teeth dropping out, the optick juices of the eye drying up, the brain, with all its de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fences, ſhatter'd, the circulation of the
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:103312:8"/>blood ſlow and languid:</q> This is an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>avoidable diſeaſe in nature, and cloſeth in the diſſolution of the whole. But then,</p>
            <p n="2">2. The common accidents of life point to us the incidency of humane nature to bodily diſeaſes. The conſtant returns of Spring and Autumn, peſtilential airs, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>healthy ſeaſons, immoderate exerciſe, or ſlothfull and undiſturb'd eaſe, unwholſome diet ſurfeits, either by exceſs, or ſomething not of agreeable digeſtion; maims or bruiſes, by falls or quarrels; natural pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſities deriv'd from the loins of diſeas'd parents when the <hi>ſtamina vitae,</hi> the firſt threds of life (if I may ſo expreſs it) are wove amiſs; and numberleſs other acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents, which time wou'd fail to reckon up, do neceſſarily expoſe the whole race of Mankind to diſtemper and infirmity, that might every moment take off the luſtre and deſirableneſs of life.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Laſtly, I add alſo, a Conſideration of Sin, and our fatal Apoſtaſie from God, which was indeed the great and onely in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>let to all humane Calamity. For without this, that Divine Hand that made us, wou'd, have ſecur'd us againſt all the accidents of
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:103312:8"/>our nice and tender compoſure. It was Sin that brought ſickneſs and diſorder upon the Soul and Body of our firſt Parents, which <hi>Adam</hi> cou'd not but derive upon his Poſterity, when he muſt needs beget one in his own Likeneſs, and after his own Image. <hi>By one man</hi> (ſaith the Apoſtle) <hi>ſin entred into the world, and death by ſin,</hi> Rom. 5.12. Now Sickneſs is the harbinger of Death, and had its ſame, both way, and time of entry into the World with Death it ſelf. It was Sin that made the healthy and well temper'd Climate of Paradiſe too hot for our firſt Parents. Sin that made the Earth ſo pregnant with noxious Vapours, and other fatal iſſues of her Womb, Sin that brought that Univerſal Curſe upon the Creation, that every thing prov'd ſo un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kindly that had been made either for ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice or ſuſtenance. Sin that occaſion'd that intire ſicklineſs in the whole Conſtitution of nature, that tainted our very Birth and Original, who otherwiſe muſt have come into the World with that equal poiſe of temper, that nothing wou'd have mov'd diſorderly within, nothing have aſſoulted impetuouſly without, ſo as to have blaſted
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:103312:9"/>or impair'd this noble compoſure of ours, till it had pleas'd God, in all the gentle diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſals of his Providence, to have call'd us out of this ſphere of action, to the immediate enjoyment of himſelf.</p>
            <p>Some uſefull reflections upon this ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervable.</p>
            <p n="1">1. By all that has been ſaid, what rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons have we of thankfulneſs, for every mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments enjoyment or continuance of health; it is that which is ſo much the bright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and joy of preſent life, that, without it, no other advantages of Nature or Art can make the enjoyment of life ſo much as tolerable, much leſs deſirable; and yet it is what may be broke in upon ſo eaſily, that nothing but one-continu'd wonder of Divine Providence preſerves it entire to any one of us. <hi>Bleſs the Lord, O my Soul, who healeth all thy diſeaſes—who redeemeth thy life from deſtruction,</hi> &amp;c. ſaith the Pſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſt.</p>
            <p n="2">2. As we ſhould be thankfull for Health, ſo alſo ſubmiſſive in Sickneſs. It is, we ſee, the common lot of humane Nature, the
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:103312:9"/>Seeds of which we take in with our firſt Being. Diſeaſes and Maladies are the Rods in God's hand to diſcipline the good, and puniſh the bad. Nay, I may further add, They are frequently the natural products of ſome men's ſins, that do neceſſarily fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low ſuch or ſuch vicious ways of life; upon all which accounts we are owing to the good pleaſure of the Divine Will, where we enjoy ſo great a bleſſing any one day, and have reaſon to ſubmit when it is other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe. So much for that firſt Obſervable.</p>
            <p n="2">II. Come we, ſecondly, to obſerve, That ſickneſs, and bodily diſeaſes, have a great deal of inſtruction in them, and it pleaſes God frequently to inflict them for this very end; that Men might thereby be brought to the knowledge of themſelves, and their duty toward Him. This I gather from the drift of the argument that <hi>Elihu</hi> is upon, wherein he is ſhowing the various ways God had to teach and inſtruct Mankind; partly by <hi>Viſions and Dreams in the night,</hi> ſtrong and divine Impreſſions upon the Mind, which were never diſpens'd or in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulg'd,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:103312:10"/>but to thoſe who by wiſdom and ſeriouſneſs, frequent Contemplation of God, and ſtrictneſs in ſerving him, had been pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſpos'd to ſuch Condeſcentions of Grace; And partly by ſickneſs and bodily diſeaſes, which he us'd as the more common means of reducing the diſobedient, when they had given up themſelves to all forgetfulneſs of God, contempt of Religion, and neglect of their immortal Souls. Now that the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendment and bettering of Men by theſe preſent chaſtiſements, is the main end and deſign that God has in all, and that in his Viſitations of this kind, there is very viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble inſtruction, ſuch as the meaneſt under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtandings may eaſily arrive at, may ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear either from a Conſideration of God, or the Calamity it ſelf.</p>
            <p n="1">1. From a Conſideration of God, who has all along made it plain in the Revela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of his Word, that he has that Love and Good-will to Mankind, that he never afflicts them for Affliction's ſake, as delight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in their Groans, or thinking his Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raignty beſt exercis'd by continu'd methods of puniſhment. He aſſures us, that <hi>in all
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:103312:10"/>our afflictions he is afflicted,</hi> Iſa. 63.9. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides, that he has given actual demonſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of this by his Providences. What o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther reaſon can be given that we at any time enjoy a moments health? God has the diſpoſal of our Tempers and Conſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, of the Air we breath in, the Food we eat, of the Seaſons of the Year, the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluences of the Stars, the Vapours of the Earth, and what-ever might miniſter either to Sickneſs or Health; that in the leaſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erting of his Power, our Beauty and Gloſs, Strength and Vigour might conſume away like a Moth fretting a garment. So that our poſſeſſing a moments health, is a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtration of the kindneſs and tenderneſs of Providence, that he do's not bring in theſe Calamities upon Men, meerly for the delight he hath in grieving them, but when it proves unavoidably neceſſary ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to <hi>chaſtiſe</hi> or <hi>correct</hi> their follies. <hi>The fooliſhneſs of Man perverteth his</hi> own <hi>ways;</hi> however, his <hi>heart</hi> at that time, and in that calamity, may <hi>fret againſt God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:103312:11"/>
2. Conſider we the Calamity it ſelf, and what natural inſtruction ariſes thence: For inſtance.</p>
            <p n="1">1. By Diſeaſes and Sickneſs, we are taught the abſolute Vanity and uncertainty of this World, with all the Comforts of it; the beauty of all vaniſheth before us upon a Sick-bed. What pleaſure can the man, in the height of an acute diſtemper take, in his Honours, his large Fortunes, his beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifull Wife, his witty Children, and all his other Conveniencies of life! Much leſs, what reliſh can we ſuppoſe he has, in thoſe Luſts of his, which once ſeem'd to admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter ſuch high ſatisfaction! Alas! all this is gone; the diſorder within has taken off the <hi>guſto</hi> of all this; and he can as little taſt the pleaſures of life, as he can his or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary food, which now is grown nauſeous and intolerable.</p>
            <p n="2">2. By Sickneſs we gain an eaſier inſight into our own guilt, and all the unreaſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble provocations we have given the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty, throughout the whole Courſe of our Lives: Sometimes the Sin is read in the very diſtemper it ſelf: Some feel their
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:103312:11"/>exceſs and intemperance, in the flames of their Feaver: Some their uncleanneſs in their Aches or Ulcers; others their ſloth and idleneſs in the ill habits of body they have thereby contracted. However, under any calamity of this kind, we have reaſon to remember Sin in general, and our Sins in particular, becauſe we may be aſſur'd, that the one is the direct fruit and product of the other. This is the Seaſon therefore, for reflecting upon loſs of Time, and a vain expence of all the precious moments of Life: the profuſe embezzelling our Talents, our Parts, or other Truſts depoſited with us for Purpoſes, to which we have not us'd or improv'd them.</p>
            <p>This is the ſeaſon of apprehending the diſpleaſure of God, which, if in theſe leſs inſtances, it becomes ſo irkſome and grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vous, it may make us think how intolera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble it would prove, ſhould the whole Viols of it be pour'd out upon us in the other World. This, in a word, is a juſt ſeaſon of repreſenting Death, and Judgment, and Eternity to our Thoughts; by all which we may grow wiſer and better in all the fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:103312:12"/>management of that life that God may yet allot to us. Here is matter of ſufficient inſtruction, and that which Diſeaſes and Sickneſs moſt naturally, and moſt reaſonably lead us out to diſcern and ponder on.</p>
            <p>To cloſe this ſecond Obſervable, as uſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully as may be, let me give one hint or two.</p>
            <p n="1">1. That if any of us have known what a fit of Sickneſs is, we would remember, and run over all thoſe thoughts and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions of Mind we felt at that time. It is hardly to be avoided at ſuch a time, but that the follies of ſome will ſtare them in the face, will extort Confeſſions from them, will put them upon vehement reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutions, and hearty promiſes of amendment, if God would pleaſe to ſpare them but this once. This is an entertainment the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter familiarly meets with, in his attendan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces on Sick-beds. How ſenſible are ſuch of their former miſcarriages! How reſolv'd to change ſo fooliſh and provoking a Courſe of life, they have hitherto led, if mercifull
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:103312:12"/>Providence would vouchſafe their recovery! Would to God ſuch were as capable of practiſing the wiſe inſtructions of Sickneſs, as they were receptive and apprehenſive of them at that time! That they would keep up the warmth of thoſe Thoughts upon the return of Health, that had been en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kindled by Sickneſs, and the proſpect of Death! Conſider this one thing; that if, upon recovery from Sickneſs, you forget thoſe inſtructions which that Seaſon gave you, and violate thoſe ſolemn engagements you then put your ſelves under, you may both lay your ſelves open to ſome new in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of God's diſpleaſure, and a more fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal ſeizure that may end in Death: And alſo, you may have ſteel'd your Minds with an acquir'd hardneſs and impenitency of Temper, that perhaps none of thoſe kindly impreſſions may ever return more, and the next paſſage from a Sick-bed, may be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a miſerable Eternity.</p>
            <p n="2">2. If you ever do fall under this diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline of the Almighty, remember to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove this advantage, where it may lye within your reach, of a <hi>Meſſenger, an Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preter,
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:103312:13"/>one among a thouſand,</hi> which may be ſo uſefull, and ſerve to ſo good purpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes at that time. Which leads to the laſt Obſervable in the Text.</p>
            <p n="3">III. Laſtly, I obſerve to you, how great a bleſſing of Providence it is, and what an allay to ſo great a Calamity, if we have the advantage of a <hi>Meſſenger,</hi> an <hi>Interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,</hi> &amp;c. that may be helpfull to us, in any of the difficulties of that Seaſon.</p>
            <p>Some, by this paſſage in my Text, would underſtand the Miniſtry of an <hi>Angel;</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs'd by theſe Titles, <hi>Meſſenger, Interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, One among a thouſand.</hi> And indeed, in the Times when there was nothing of a ſtanding, reveal'd Rule and Law of Faith and Practice, it is not improbable but the Miniſtry of Angels was more frequently and more viſibly indulg'd toward good Men. And queſtionleſs, it was a pure mark of Divine Favour, where the Sick perſon at any time met with ſuch Conde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcentions of Grace, that ſuch an <hi>One</hi> of all thoſe <hi>thouſands</hi> that attend the Throne of
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:103312:13"/>God, ſhould ſtand at his Bed-ſide, to enno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble his Mind with wiſer and clearer Noti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of God, more comfortable proſpects of another World, or a pleaſing aſſurance of a longer date and term of years here. But this we need not either ſtretch, or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fine this paſſage to.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Elihu</hi> ſeems to hint to <hi>Job,</hi> the preſent mixtures and allays of Divine Goodneſs, in that while God had brought <hi>Job</hi> into ſo deplorable a condition, by ſickneſs and pains of the worſt kind; yet he had con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſcended to furniſh him with religious, uſefull, and excellent Friends, that might interpret to him the Will and Meaning of God in this preſent Diſpenſation, and might pray for the removal of ſo ſad an affliction from him. So that in Analogy to this, we have reaſon to account it an admirable Privilege that we may have the attendance of God's <hi>Meſſengers</hi> at our Sick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beds to aſſiſt us with their Exhortations, their Reproofs, their Directions, their Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forts, their Prayers, and all the uſefull Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plications of their Office and Miniſtry, as they may be any way ſerviceable to relieve
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:103312:14"/>us at preſent, or further us in the great Concernments of Eternity. The Privilege may appear chiefly upon theſe accounts.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The great indiſpoſedneſs that proba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly our own Minds may be in (at ſuch a time as that) to do any thing to good pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe our ſelves; the diſorder of the whole Man, when bodily pains, want of reſt, an hurry of the ſpirits, ſickneſs and nauſeouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of ſtomach, affection of the brain and the like, muſt in all likelihood greatly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terrupt all compos'd Thought or Reaſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and may eaſily take the Mind off from its greateſt Concernments by a vehement deſire of preſent eaſe and refreſhment: then to have a faithfull <hi>Meſſenger</hi> of God by us, that may put us in mind of higher things; that may help us in our Meditations; may ſupply us with Materials of Thought and Reflection; that may lead us into a ſenſe of our ſelves, and put us upon looking back upon paſt follies, and ſo help us for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward in thoſe acts of Repentance which are requir'd of us in the Goſpel; thereby ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther preparing us for Heaven, or making
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:103312:14"/>us more fit to live in this World, if reſtor'd and recover'd. Surely this is of great ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage, which a good Mind would be apt to eſteem as ſome way Compenſating for all the uneaſineſs and other troubleſome Appendages of a Sick-bed.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The great Miſtakes we may be apt to fall under at ſuch a time, makes it of great advantage to us, to be under the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection and ſteerage of ſuch an one. Our own Organs of Thinking may then be ſo much out of order, that we may not have the ſame Idea's of Things which in our Health and Vigor of Reaſoning we have once had. But beſides that, there is a moſt buſie Adverſary that neglects no ſuch op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunities of attacking the weak and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>abled Powers of Mind at that time. He will then be caſting all the Blinds, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſenting all the falſe Scenes imaginable. Sometimes he will flatter the Man into a <hi>better</hi> opinion of himſelf than he ought to have, by which he would prevent his ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary Repentance. Here the faithful <hi>Meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenger,</hi> and due <hi>Interpreter</hi> of things, is infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitely
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:103312:15"/>uſefull: To let a Man ſee himſelf and his lamentable Condition through Sin; the need he has of the great Expiation; the neceſſity of Repentance, and earneſt im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity with God for Pardon and For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giveneſs. Sometimes again, he will encreaſe and aggravate the Sinner's guilt beyond all <hi>juſt</hi> meaſures, as if his Sins, both for the number, and the nature of them, were be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond the compaſs of Divine Grace. Here again, the <hi>Meſſenger,</hi> the <hi>Interpreter,</hi> the <hi>One among a thouſand,</hi> comes in ſeaſonably, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plains the Nature of the New Covenant, recites and inſiſts upon the Promiſes, which are as large and boundleſs as our Sins have been; and have no feebler a Confirmation, than the Blood of <hi>Jeſus,</hi> and the Oath of <hi>God.</hi> He informs him of the Nature of true Repentance; and by the juſt Notes of it, ſhows him, that what he now acts is true and real; Nay, he can lay open thoſe very <hi>Wiles of the Devil,</hi> by which he would <hi>at that time,</hi> be perplexing his Faith and Hopes in God. In a word, ſometimes the Devil will be aggrandizing the affliction it ſelf, as if it were out of the ordinary way of
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:103312:15"/>Providence, and an evident token of God's Wrath; or that it is not what he has de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerv'd, but what he may juſtly murmure and repine at. Here this excellent <hi>Interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> can, by a skilfull reading upon Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, let the Man ſee, that <hi>no temptation has befallen him, but what is common to Man;</hi> that <hi>no Man knows love or hatred by theſe things;</hi> that affliction is ſo far from being the mark of God's wrath, or of a reprobate ſtate, that it is rather a token of his tender and fatherly compaſſion, who therefore <hi>chaſtiſeth,</hi> becauſe he <hi>loveth</hi> them, and would do them good in the latter end; that it is far <hi>leſs than his iniquities deſerve,</hi> and that therefore there is all the reaſon in the World for his entire ſubmiſſion and reſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation. In theſe and other caſes where the <hi>Clinick</hi> is ſo prone to miſtakes concerning either himſelf or God; how uſefull may ſuch an excellent Perſon be to <hi>interpret</hi> to him the Word and Providences of God, to keep him right in all juſt Idea's and Apprehenſions of things!</p>
            <p n="3">
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:103312:16"/>
3. Laſtly, He is of further advantage to implore God in the behalf of ſuch, either for the removal of his hand, or for a good iſſue and concluſion in the end; It is no ordinary Privilege that, when our own Minds perhaps are ſharing in the diſorders of our Bodies, we ſhould then have the Prayers of ſome good Men, who, in a fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low-feeling of our infirmities, can heartily and in earneſt recommend us to God. <hi>The effectual fervent prayer of a righteous Man a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vaileth much,</hi> Jam. 5.16. Hence his directi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to the faithfull, that <hi>if any be ſick among them,</hi> they ſhould <hi>call for the Elders of the Church,</hi> and <hi>they ſhall pray over them</hi>—and <hi>the prayer of Faith ſhall ſave the ſick, and the Lord ſhall raiſe him up,</hi> ver. 14, 15. We don't indeed, with thoſe of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> pretend to keep up the Ceremony of <hi>anointing with Oyl,</hi> which is alſo directed in this place; becauſe the Power it ſelf, that is, the gift of Healing, of which this Uncti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on was the Symbol, is ſo long ceas'd, and therefore it is highly proper that the Sym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bol it ſelf ſhould ceaſe too. But Prayer is
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:103312:16"/>a ſtanding Duty, and hath its abiding Ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects; if not in the actual recovery of the Man (which yet not improbably has been frequently obtain'd by Prayer) however may not prove ineffectual, as to his Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Salvation; both which ſeem to be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehended in this laſt paſſage of my Text: <hi>Then he is gracious unto him, and ſaith, De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liver him from going down into the pit; I have found a ranſom.</hi> This might lead me into a large field of diſcourſe, but I will ſhut up the whole, with an uſefull In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference or two.</p>
            <p n="1">1. We may hence learn to live under a daily wiſe expectation of ſuch a Calamity as this. Our ſins and follies of Life may eaſily provoke God. Our frail and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noxious Nature daily expoſes us; and Old Age, which is one continu'd and unavoid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Sickneſs, will ere long creep upon the ſtrongeſt of us, which therefore may put the wiſeſt of us into a juſt expectation of ſuch an hour. But then,</p>
            <p n="2">2. If it ſhould be our lot to be thus dealt with, let us not deſpiſe this indulgence
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:103312:17" rendition="simple:additions"/>of Providence, the Helps and Miniſtries of him whom God hath appointed his <hi>Meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenger,</hi> his <hi>Interpreter;</hi> that he may mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter to us in all thoſe uſefull aſſiſtances, of which we may then ſtand in ſo much need, and for which the Church has ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly provided ſuch tender and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſive Offices.</p>
            <closer>Now to God the Father, God the Son, and God the Holy Ghoſt, be all Honour, and Glory, and Praiſe, now and for ever. <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </closer>
            <trailer>THE END.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
